Pearce Family Papers, 1880-1962
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Pearce Family Papers
1880-1962
Pearce family
MS 119
3 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The papers represent the extended Pearce/Brown family involved in education in rural United States and missionary and education work at the Sidon Female Seminary in Syria and elswhere in the Middle East, circa 1880s-1930s. Also represented are Eleanor I. Burns, founder of the American College for Girls in Istanbul; Mary Mills Patrick, founder of Constantinople Women's College; and Alice Lloyd, founder of Caney Junior College in Kentucky.
Biographical Note
Primary family members represented in papers include Charlotte Hays Brown (1862- 1951), who served in Syria under the auspices of the Foreign Missions of the Presbyterian Church from 1885-1931. For much of that time she was principal of the Sidon Female Seminary. She later lived in Lebanon. Her sister, Rebecca McClure (Brown) Pearce (1860-1911) was also a missionary in Syria from 1885-92. Rebecca's daughter, Katherine Standish Pearce (1895- 1990) graduated Smith College, 1915; taught languages and was librarian at Constantinople Women's College, Turkey, 1925-31, and was cataloger at the Princeton University Library, 1931-61. Katherine's sister, Charlotte Crosby Pearce (1894-1919), also graduated Smith College 1915.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Pearce Family Papers represent the extended Pearce/Brown family involved in education in under served areas in the rural United States and missionary and education work in the Middle East, circa 1880s-1930s. Also represented are Eleanor I. Burns, founder of the American College for Girls in Istanbul; Mary Mills Patrick, founder of Constantinople Women's College; and Alice Lloyd, founder of Caney Junior College in Kentucky. The collection includes biographical and genealogical information; correspondence (1892-1962); photographs; scrapbook; travel diary from European trip (1953); and writings (1911-53). Pamphlets and reports relating to the Sidon Female Seminary are of particular interest.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Search Terms
Brown, Charlotte Hays, 1862-1951; Patrick, Mary Mills, 1850-1940; Pearce, Charlotte Crosby, 1894-1919; Pearce, Katherine Standish, 1895-1990; Pearce, Rebecca McClure Brown, 1860-1911; Brown family; Pearce family; American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey); Sidon Female Seminary; Education--Turkey--History--Sources; Missionaries--Middle East--Biography--Sources; Syria--History--Sources; Turkey--History--1918-1960--Sources; Women missionaries--Middle East--Biography--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Brown Family Papers are located at Princeton University.
Additional material on Charlotte and Katherine Pearce is located in the Student files of the Smith College Archives.
Contents List
  - Biography and memorabilia
    - Brown Family tree (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Charlotte Hays Brown (Box 1)
      - Clippings, articles, miscellaneous biographical material, 1936-52 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Passports, 1925, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Arthur J. Brown: clippings, 1951-62 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Eleanor I. Burns: clippings and articles, 1950-52 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alice Lloyd: clippings and articles, 1961-62, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Mary Mills Patrick: clippings and articles, 1927-64 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Charlotte Crosby Pearce: obituary, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Katharine Standish Pearce
      - Teaching contracts, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Constantinople Women's College: library lists, 1927-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Green Pyne Leaf" (Princeton University Library staff publication,) 1951-61 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Rebecca Brown Pearce
      - Small book given to her on her birthday, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Sidon Seminary, Syria: reports, notes and printed material, 1880-92 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous memorabilia, 1888-1929, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings: Katharine Standish Pearce
    - Trip to Europe, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1911-53 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence
    - From Katharine Standish Pearce (Box 2)
      - Family, 1920-28 (Box 2, Folder 3-10)
      - Margaret Storrs Grierson, 1950-66 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - To Katharine Standish Pearce
      - Annie E. Brown, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Arthur J. Brown, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Eleanor Lyons Brown, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Frederick W. Brown, 1921, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Wilma Brown, 1923? (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Elsa Kimball, 1955-62, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Henry Leiper, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Alice Lloyd, 1921-23 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Mary Mills Patrick, 1921-28, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Charlotte C. Pearce, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Miscellaneous, 1924-52, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Business letters, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - From Charlotte Hays Brown (Box 2)
      - Family, 1892-1931 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "My Dear People" (from Syria), 1929-34 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Frederick T. Brown to Rebecca Brown Pearce and Mary L. Brown, 1873-88 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Frederick Leiper, letters to him, 1911-13 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Edgar Pearce to Cohen Pearce, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Irving Pearce to Cohen Pearce, 1882 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - To Rebecca Brown Pearce, 1884-98 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lois Wilson to Mary Brown Leiper, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Letters to Miss Adams, 1950-53 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Miscellaneous, 1904, 1951, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Photographs
    - Rebecca Brown Pearce, 1888, 1955, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Charlotte Hays Brown, 1885-1955 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mary Mills Patrick, 1940-43, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Lebanon, Syria, and Europe, 1910, 1923-26, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous, mostly groups, 1895-34, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Sidon Seminary, Syria, 1887-1931, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sketches by Charlotte H. Brown (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook of Mary Brown Leiper, circa 1930s (Box 3)